Welcome to the Deep Dive. I am, uh, I'm just so glad you were joining us today because we
are going into some truly mind-bending territory. Oh, absolutely. It's a heavy one today. Yeah,
it really is. So to get started, I want you to imagine building a house. Usually, you know,
you have a master blueprint. Right. You know exactly how the plumbing connects to the walls
and how the roof sits on the frame. It's supposed to be a single, solid, interconnected structure.
Yeah, exactly. The physics of the structure basically demand consistency. I mean,
a wooden door cannot simply open into a solid brick wall. Every individual piece of that house
has to agree with the reality of the pieces surrounding it. But imagine if you hired
10 different contractors, put them all in blindfolds, and just told each one to build
their own specific room perfectly. Oh boy. Right. Oh. And they are never allowed to check
if their room actually connects to the rest of the house. You'd end up with a building
that looks totally fine if you only stand in one room. Yeah. But globally, it's a complete
disaster. Yeah. Absolute chaos. You'd have, like, staircases leading to nowhere and pipes venting
water directly into the living room. And that, strangely enough, is a very accurate description
of how we have been building artificial intelligence for the last decade.
Which brings us to the focus of today's deep dive. We've got a massive stack of notes here
on a fascinating and honestly highly technical 2026 monograph.
Very technical. Yeah. It's by an independent researcher named Flyxion. It is titled Tartan,
Trajectory Aware Recursive Tiling with Annotated Noise. Okay, let's unpack this. The title alone
is incredibly dense. It really is a mouthful. But the mission of this deep dive is to look at a wild
fundamental shift proposed in this paper. What if we stop teaching machines to just, you know,
predict the next word or the next pixel and instead teach them to construct a globally consistent
reality? It's a massive shift away from treating machine inference as just a statistical guessing
game. Flyxion is arguing that we need to move toward treating inference as what the paper calls
constraint closure. Constraint closure. Okay. Yeah. And for anyone trying to understand why modern AI
still hallucinates or fails to connect the dots in a logical way, this paper is an absolute gold
mine. I promise you by the end of our time today, you are going to look at machine learning and perhaps
even the way your own brain structures knowledge in a completely different way. I'm so ready for this.
But to understand Tartan, we first have to understand the fundamental flaw in current machine
learning that it was built to solve, right? Exactly. The paper is pretty brutal about this right out at
the gate. It just critiques the entire dominant paradigm of how we train models. It really doesn't
hold back. The critique centers on how current models operate by estimating conditional distributions.
In simple terms, they take an input, which we can call variable X, and they try to predict an output,
variable Y. Right. Like guessing the next word in a sentence. Precisely. The models optimize each of
these observations or predictions independently. They're basically just asking, given X, what is
the most statistically probable Y? Over and over again. But Flyxion points out a massive structural
flaw here. By optimizing these predictions individually, the system completely abandons the requirement
that all these observations must actually be able to coexist in the real world. So it's the
blindfolded contractors again. Exactly. Each prediction might be statistically likely on its
own, but the system isn't checking if they fit together into a logical whole. The paper refers to this
as predictive inconsistency. The predictive paradigm ignores the fact that observations in the real world
are not independent targets. They are coupled together. They affect each other. Right. They
are projections of a shared underlying world state. If a system optimizes them without a shared
constraint, it might achieve local accuracy, but it results in global fragmentation. That is the
literal root cause of an AI hallucination. Man, it's like looking at a beautiful landscape
through a dozen tiny plastic straws. Oh, that's a good way to put it. You could paint exactly what
you see through each individual straw perfectly. But when you lay all those tiny paintings out on a
table together, rivers are suddenly flowing uphill and shadows are pointing in three different
directions. Yes. You end up painting an M.C. Escher painting. It looks totally right locally inside each
straw, but it is physically impossible globally. So how does Tartan actually fix this? Because tossing
out the entire prediction model sounds like a monumental task. Well, if we connect this to the
bigger picture, Flyxion argues that a system shouldn't just guess the most statistically likely
output. Instead, it must find an admissible state. Admissible state. Yes. This means finding a state where
all observations agree with underlying physical dynamics. The paper grounds this approach in
something it calls the RSVP field theory, which stands for relativistic scalar vector plenum. Okay,
wait, wait. I'm going to need you to slow down and translate that for me. Relativistic scalar vector
plenum. That sounds like deep theoretical physics, not computer science. How does a computer program use
physics? It's basically a theoretical framework borrowed from physics to manage data. Think about
thermodynamics. Okay. In a closed physical system, energy is conserved. You can't just magically create
energy out of nowhere. It has to flow from one place to another. Right. Basic physics. So the RSVP framework
treats data probabilities like physical pressures. It tracks constraints like potential flow and entropy
across the information. Oh, wow. So instead of an AI just guessing the next word, the inference process
becomes a dynamical search for a fixed point where every single data constraint is satisfied
simultaneously. The AI is essentially balancing a massive chemical equation. That is wild. All the
parts have to sum correctly without violating the thermodynamics of the system's logic.
So it is not about finding the closest guess. It is about reconstructing a coherent reality
where all the pieces actually fit together. Exactly. I mean, that makes sense conceptually,
but practically. Rebuilding a coherent world from scratch every time sounds like an impossible
computational bottleneck. And that brings us to the recursive titling part of the Tartan acronym.
To manage that immense computational load, the system divides all incoming data into a cover of
tiles. Okay. You can visualize this as a spatial grid over an image or a temporal grid over a sequence
of events. Each individual tile computes its own local state, ensuring that it satisfies its own local
admissibility constraints based on the data it holds. So we are back to the contractors in their individual
rooms. Each tile is its own little world trying to make sense of its own data. Well, it starts that way,
yes. But the critical innovation happens at the boundaries between those tiles. It overlaps.
Right. Traditional computer models treat the overlaps between regions as passive boundaries,
just places where data is awkwardly handed off or blended. Tartan elevates these overlaps to first
class computational objects. The overlap is where the system actively hunts for discrepancies between
neighboring tiles. Wait, wait, I am genuinely a little lost here. Why would it hunt for discrepancies?
Instead of just smoothing over the errors like a photo filter, which is what I feel like most algorithms
do to make things look nice and seamless, it actively zeros in on the seams? Yeah, it does.
Why highlight the broken parts? Because in Flyxion's framework, error is not just a simple number to be
minimized. In traditional AI, you have a loss function, which basically just tells the computer,
you're 10% wrong, try to be less wrong. Right. But in Tartan, the discrepancy calculated in the overlap
is called a defect tensor. It's a structured topological barrier. The paper uses categorical
language and calls it a cohomological obstruction. A cohomological obstruction. That is quite the
phrase to drop into a conversation. I know, it's dense. What does a topological barrier actually look
like inside a computer? Think of it as a geometric map of how the worldview is breaking down. It's not
just a generic error notification. It is highly structured information telling the system exactly
why the two tiles cannot coexist in the same reality. Oh, I see. Imagine trying to stitch a
completely flat paper map onto a spherical globe. You are going to get crinkles and tears. A cohomological
obstruction is the mathematical shape of that tear. It tells the system, you cannot close this loop
because your fundamental geometry is wrong. I love that. It is not just saying error 404. It is
providing a topographical map of the failure itself. And once Tartan finds these structured defects in
the overlaps, the paper outlines a very specific three-step hierarchy for how the system is supposed
to fix them. Right. The staged closure protocol. Exactly. Staged closure protocol. How does that work?
Well, the system analyzes the signature of that defect tensor to understand the nature of the failure
and then applies the minimal modification necessary to restore compatibility across the boundary.
The first step it attempts is called gauge repair. Which, if I am reading this right,
is essentially a coordinate mismatch. If we have two map makers drawing the exact same coastline,
but one is using miles and the other is using kilometers, the overlap won't match.
Exactly. But you don't need to redraw the coast. You just need to align the scales.
The math behind gauge repair handles exactly that kind of superficial translation.
It vanishes under normalization. But if aligning the scales doesn't fix the tear in the map,
the system moves to the second step, which is refinement. Okay. Refinement.
This deals with resolution issues. The system subdivides the tile to get a much closer look.
The underlying assumption here is that the discrepancy might be hiding in a high-frequency
detail that was simply blurred out in the coarse, zoomed-out view.
But what if it is not a scale issue and zooming in doesn't reveal any new hidden details? Like,
the two tiles still fundamentally disagree on what reality looks like.
Then the system hits the third, and frankly most profound, step. State extension.
State extension.
Yeah. This means the system realizes it is fundamentally missing a piece of reality.
Its current understanding of the universe is too small to explain the data.
So it has to introduce a new latent variable. It literally enlarges its own state space so that
a compatible configuration becomes mathematically possible.
Okay. Let me try to ground this with a real-world analogy.
Please do.
Say I am tracking a moving car on a security camera feed, and it suddenly vanishes from the screen.
Gauge repair is me checking if my camera just got bumped and lost its coordinate alignment.
Right.
Refinement is me zooming in on the pixels to see if the car is just hiding in a really dark shadow.
Exactly.
But state extension is me realizing, oh, tunnels exist. I have to invent a completely new concept,
a tunnel, to make my worldview make sense again.
That perfectly captures the mechanics of it. The system is expanding its ontology,
and that leads directly to one of the most compelling concepts in the paper, ontological growth.
Yeah.
Tartan maintained something called an obstruction log.
An obstruction log.
Yeah, you can think of it as a learned atlas of past failures.
Like a diary of every time it realized a new concept, like a tunnel, had to exist.
Precisely.
When a novel failure occurs, the system references this log.
If the existing repertoire of repairs cannot fix the new obstruction,
it expands its worldview by adding a new variable.
However, it only does this if the new variable meets very strict mathematical criteria,
such as explanatory compression and cross-context recurrence.
It has to be highly defensive to avoid ontological overgrowth.
Which would be the system just making up useless, overly complex variables to explain away simple static or noise.
It doesn't want to start hallucinating ghosts to explain why the car disappeared.
Exactly.
But that brings up a huge issue for me.
What happens if the data itself is just lying?
Like, how does the system know when to fundamentally change its worldview versus when to just ignore a broken camera?
Af Flyxion anticipates that exact vulnerability.
The paper refers to this problem as malignant novelty.
Sometimes a defect in the overlap isn't a brilliant new discovery like a tunnel.
It's just a broken camera lens, a calibration drift, or even a deliberate adversarial manipulation of the data.
And if the system blindly accepts a broken camera lens as a brand new law of physics,
the paper says it creates an explanation sink.
Right.
It is basically a totally useless variable that just absorbs errors but doesn't actually interact with the rest of the world.
An explanation sink violates the principle of causal reciprocity.
Think about your tunnel analogy.
If a tunnel is real, it has to interact with other features of the world.
It casts a shadow, it echoes sound, it displaces earth.
Yeah, that makes sense.
But a smudge on a camera lens only affects that one specific lens.
It doesn't cast a shadow on the actual street.
Here's where it gets really interesting.
Tartan actually has a defensive inference branch specifically designed to handle this malignant data.
It does.
It can put lying sensors into quarantine.
It literally isolates them from the main reconstruction pipeline so they cannot infect the global worldview.
And then it tests those quarantine sensors using something called modality ablation.
I just love that concept.
It's a great term.
It essentially asks, if I close this eye, does the anomaly disappear?
If yes, the eye is the problem, not the world.
Modality ablation is a rigorous test for cross-context transportability.
By systematically shutting down different data inputs, ablating the modalities, the system isolates the source of the defect.
If a defect is a real feature of the world, it should show up across multiple observational pathways.
Right.
If it only exists in the data stream of one isolated sensor, that sensor remains in quarantine.
But the paper notes it doesn't just permanently delete the sensor, which feels counterintuitive to me.
I mean, if a camera is broken, why not just turn it off forever?
Because completely discarding data limits the system's future resilience.
Instead, the system builds an explicit mathematical model of the sensor's corruption.
Once it maps exactly how the sensor is broken, the sensor is placed on probation.
Probation for a sensor? That's hilarious.
It really is.
Okay, so up to this point, this all sounds like incredible, but highly theoretical physics and math.
We are talking about constraints, manifolds, topologies, and ablations.
But the paper argues Tartan isn't just a theory.
It actually explains empirical breakthroughs that are happening right now in AI and software engineering.
Yes.
The paper makes a very compelling pivot to empirical data by referencing a 2025 study by Chang, Broadbent, and Chappell.
That study looked at large language models utilizing CLIO, which stands for Cognitive Loop via In-Situ Optimization.
I remember reading about that study.
They found that an AI's accuracy improved wildly when the system was allowed to oscillate in its uncertainty.
Exactly.
When the AI wasn't sure of an answer, instead of just forcing a prediction, it would loop and oscillate internally before finally settling on an output.
And Flyxion's math attempts to prove why that oscillation actually works.
Flyxion provides the exact structural grounding that the researchers were missing.
Those internal oscillations are not just random noise or numerical instability, which is what many engineers assumed at the time.
Right.
When the AI oscillates, it means it is hitting a structural mathematical wall, one of those cohomological obstructions we discussed earlier.
Yeah.
The system is navigating near the absolute boundary of what its current worldview can explain, and that looping is the mathematical process of trying to find a repair path.
So it is pacing back and forth in front of a giant wall, trying to figure out if it needs to find a ladder, grab a sledgehammer, or if it just needs to invent the concept of a door.
That's exactly it.
If the uncertainty simply decayed in a straight line, it would mean the problem was trivial.
But persistent oscillation means the system has recognized a profound structural defect and is actively performing constraint closure.
The AI is structurally reconfiguring its own latent space to accommodate reality.
And this brings up a thought.
If this math perfectly describes how an AI hits a wall and has to structurally repair its worldview, could this same math fix regular human-written software?
I mean, I am looking at the section of the paper on semantic merge, and it blew my mind.
Think about version control for coders, like Git.
Right now, if two developers edit a software file at the same time, the computer just violently mashes the text together.
If there's a conflict, it throws its hands up and makes the humans figure it out.
Traditional version control is incredibly primitive in that regard.
It treats code purely as a sequence of text strings, rather than as a structured object with inherent meaning and operational invariance.
But Tartan proposes doing this semantically merging the actual meaning of the code.
The paper introduces this concept called homotope kalimates.
It argues we should treat a software-emerge conflict exactly like an AI hallucination.
It is not just a text error.
It is a structural defect in the overlaps between two developers' worldviews.
Homotope kalimates allow the system to map the underlying mathematical skeleton that both pieces of code share.
Instead of comparing the raw text, it compares the function and intent.
If the skeletons conflict, the system applies the exact same staged closure, protocol gauge repair, refinement, or state extension to merge the operation safely.
This raises an important question, though.
If software collaboration, AI reasoning, and physical constraint closure are all governed by the exact same mathematical topology, what does that say about the nature of knowledge itself?
So, what does this all mean for you listening to this right now?
The epistemology section of this paper gets deeply philosophical.
It suggests that inference, the act of learning and knowing, isn't just abstract thought.
It is a physical process constrained by the same laws as thermodynamics.
The act of inference is portrayed as a dynamical process where any system, biological or artificial, evolves toward a configuration of maximal coherence with its environment.
And the most beautiful part is that it inherently embodies a principle of ontological humility.
Ontological humility.
Yes.
The mathematics of Tartan literally assume that the system's initial worldview is incomplete.
It only expands its understanding of reality when it is absolutely forced to by consistent cross-context evidence that its current map is broken.
Ontological humility.
I mean, we could all probably use a little more of that.
The system isn't trying to force the world to fit what it already knows.
It is constantly searching the overlaps for where its worldview breaks down and using those exact fractures to build a better, more complete reality.
Exactly.
The power of seeking global consistency over localized correctness is something that extends far beyond computer science.
I want to leave you with a final thought directly from Flyxion's text.
The author writes,
Identity, in this context, is defined by the persistence of a trajectory under constraint.
A system maintains its identity not by preserving a static pattern, but by sustaining a coherent evolution within the admissible manifold.
That is heavy.
It really makes you ponder.
In your own life, are you trying to maintain your identity by rigidly holding on to static patterns and ignoring the overlaps?
Or are you allowing yourself to coherently evolve when the defects of the real world challenge your worldview?
Are you just building your one room blindfolded?
Or are you willing to take the blindfold off and look at the whole house?
Keep exploring those overlaps, everyone.
Okay.
Thank you.
Bye-bye.