Welcome back to the Deep Dive. I want to start today by asking you the listener to do a quick
mental exercise with me. So think about your current primary email inbox. Oh boy, that's a
stressful start. I know, right? Just bear with me. Now, try to isolate that one specific project
thread. You know the exact one I'm talking about. Let's imagine it is a project to design a new
product. We will call it the AeroBrew 3000, like a smart coffee machine your company is trying to
launch. Okay, I can picture it. Right, so imagine the email thread for the AeroBrew 3000. It has 42
replies. It spans, I don't know, three weeks. There are five different people CC'd. Absolute nightmare
scenario. Exactly. And in paragraph two of an email sent last Tuesday, the hardware engineer stated
that the water reservoir needs to be smaller. But then on Thursday, the marketing director replied
to a completely different part of the thread, saying the overall size of the machine needs to
look imposing and large. Right, totally conflicting visions. Yeah. And then someone else chimed in with
a, you know, just my two cents about the color being matte black, ignoring the previous three emails
entirely. Because nobody actually reads the whole thread. Never. So when you open that thread,
you are not looking at a coffee machine. You are looking at a, well, a historical record of
fragmented arguments. You are forced to become a digital archaeologist. Sifting through layers of text.
Yes. Just trying to construct the current agreed upon reality of this coffee machine entirely inside
your own head. And the worst part is the four other people on that thread are doing the exact
same mental gymnastics. And arriving at completely different conclusions. Right. It is almost guaranteed
that all five of you are holding a completely different version of the AeroBrew 3000 in your minds.
It is like the absolute definition of muddy water. It is. And it's a universally exhausting
experience. But what is really insidious about it is that we tend to blame ourselves. Wait, really?
How so? Well, we assume we're just bad at managing our time or that our colleagues are poor communicators.
We think if only we had used Slack instead of email or Teams instead of Slack, this would have been
smoothed. Oh, yeah. The eternal quest for the right app. Exactly. Yeah. But we rarely step back to
question the fundamental architecture of the communication itself. We treat the exhaustion
as a personal failing rather than a structural failing of the medium we're using. Okay, let's
unpack this. Yeah. Because we are sending more messages today than at any point in human history.
We are hyper-connected. More than ever. And yet, true collaboration-like, the act of getting
multiple human minds aligned to build a single complex thing somehow feels harder than ever.
It's a massive paradox. It really is. And that contradiction is the premise of our deep dive
today. We are exploring a truly paradigm-shifting essay from April 2026. It was written by an independent
researcher named Fliction, and it carries a rather academic title. It's a mouthful for sure. Yeah. It's
called From Messages to Worlds, Transformational Communication, Semantic Version Control, and the
Collaborative Evolution of Shared State. So it is a dense, highly theoretical title. But underneath that
academic phrasing is a really functional blueprint for why our digital workspaces feel broken. Right.
And more importantly, how a very specific subset of people, software developers, have quietly
solved this problem without the rest of the world really noticing.
That's the crazy part to me. So the mission today is to completely, fundamentally upgrade how you,
the listener, understand human and artificial communication.
It's a total perspective shift.
Totally. The goal is to walk away from this deep dive, realizing that the most effective way to
communicate is not actually about passing messages back and forth. It is about collaboratively
building, modifying, and iterating on a shared reality.
A shared world.
Exactly. We are going to look at why developers use platforms like GitHub. We are going to apply
those exact same rules to why it is so frustrating to talk to an AI like JetGPD. And we are even going
to explore how societies determine what is true.
It covers a lot of ground.
It does. So to start, Flixian introduces a concept that completely changed my perspective.
They call, the way we currently use email and chat, the hydraulic view of communication.
Right. The hydraulic model is essentially the water pipe theory of human interaction.
It is deeply ingrained in us, largely because it forms the basis of early information theory.
Okay. Give me the background on that.
So back in 1948, a mathematician named Claude Shannon at Bell Labs published a landmark paper
called A Mathematical Theory of Communication.
Bell Labs. Right. So he was dealing with physical phones.
Exactly. He was dealing with physical engineering problems. He was trying to figure out how to
send an electrical signal down a long copper telephone wire without the signal getting
degraded by static.
The physical noise on the line.
Right. In his model, you have a sender who encodes a message into a signal. That signal
travels through a channel of the pipe, and a receiver decodes it on the other end.
Shannon was explicitly concerned with physical noise. If I send a binary one and it arises
a zero, that is a failure.
But Shannon himself actually warned against applying this to human meaning, didn't he?
He did. Very explicitly.
Yeah. I remember reading that he stated his theory did not care about the semantic content
of the message. The system didn't care if the binary code spelled out a profound poem
or just absolute gibberish.
It only cared that the gibberish arrived intact.
Exactly.
And that is the tragic irony of modern digital communication. We took an engineering framework
designed for copper wires and adopted it as a universal philosophy for human collaboration.
Which makes no sense when you think about it.
None at all. When you send an email about the AeroBrew 3000 coffee machine, you are acting
as the sender encoding a message. You push it through the internet pipe. If the recipient gets
the text, the software considers the communication successful.
Even if they read it and get completely the wrong idea.
Precisely. The system does not care if the recipient completely misunderstands your intent.
In the hydraulic model, misunderstanding is just treated as noise in the pipe.
Which forces everyone into that archaeological dig I mentioned earlier. Email allows you to
externalize your assertions. You can type out your opinions and send them away.
But it forces you to internalize the state.
And by state, we mean the current status of the project.
Right. The state being the actual current reality of the project.
Because there is no central coffee machine in the email thread, I have to constantly update
my mental model of the machine based on every new message that arrives.
Which is cognitively exhausting.
So exhausting. I have to remember that John vetoed the matte black color and Sarah changed
the water reservoir size. I am holding the entire complex state of the project in my limited
human working memory.
What's fascinating here is how Fliction contrasts this grueling state internalizing process with
the way software developers operate on platforms like GitHub.
Because they don't use the hydraulic model at all.
No. GitHub completely abandons it. It does not use message passing as its primary mechanism.
It uses what Fliction terms transformational communication.
Let's ground this for anyone who has never looked at a line of code or used GitHub.
How does transformational communication actually work in practice?
In a system like GitHub, the central element is the repository.
For a software team, the repository contains all the code for their application.
But conceptually, the repository is the world.
A shared sandbox.
Exactly. It is a shared, explicit object that sits in the center of the table.
When a developer wants to communicate an idea, say, they want to change the color of a login
button from blue to red, they do not send an email to the team saying, I think the button
should be red.
Because that would be a hydraulic message about the world, forcing everyone to imagine a red
button.
Precisely.
Instead, the developer actually goes into their local copy of the code, changes the specific
lines of text that govern the button's color, and submits that exact structural change as a
proposal to the central repository.
They just do the work.
Yeah, they are proposing a concrete transformation to the world.
They are saying, here is the new reality I am suggesting we adopt.
I want to try an analogy here to see if I am grasping the magnitude of this difference.
Go for it.
Let's say you and I are trying to play a highly complex game of chess.
The email method, the hydraulic model, is like us trying to play chess by mailing each other
descriptions of our moves.
Oh, that sounds awful.
It is.
It'd be like, I am moving my knight to the left side, kind of near that one pawn.
You know the one.
Neither of us actually has a physical board to look at.
We're just keeping the entire ever-changing state of the chess board in our heads.
Which works for about three moves.
Right.
By turn 15, my mental board and your mental board are completely out of sync.
I think my queen is safe.
You think you captured it three turns ago.
That captures the chaos perfectly.
The cognitive load of maintaining the board state eventually overwhelms both players, leading
to inevitable collapse.
So in contrast, GitHub is like having a physical wooden chess board sitting on a table right
between us.
An externalized state.
Yes.
When I want to make a move, I do not send you a vague description.
I physically pick up my knight, move it to a specific square, and take my hand away.
I have transformed the shared object.
You don't have to imagine my move.
You just look at the board.
The board is the communication.
And this brings up a really counterintuitive reality about transformational systems.
You might assume that because GitHub is so powerful, it must give you ultimate freedom.
That would be the logical guess.
But GitHub is actually far more rigidly constrained than email.
Think about it.
Email lets you say absolutely anything to anyone at any time.
You could reply to an email about server maintenance with a recipe for banana bread.
Or a rant about the AeroBrew 3000.
Exactly.
The system does not stop you.
I have to stop you there, though.
Are you arguing that restriction is actually the secret ingredient to good communication?
I am.
Because normally, when a manager introduces a new tool with strict rules, the team revolts.
People hate constraints.
They complain that it stifles creativity or slows them down.
How does forcing developers into a rigid box make them communicate better?
It is a completely valid pushback.
Because our instinct is always to demand more degrees of freedom.
But let's look at the nature of the restriction.
GitHub forces you to express your thoughts as highly specific, syntactic changes to targeted lines of code.
You can't just be vague.
Right.
You cannot just leave a floating comment like,
The database feels slow.
You have to highlight the exact line of code in the exact file that you believe is causing the slowdown.
And propose the exact textual change to fix it.
This constraint eliminates the most toxic element of team collaboration.
Referential ambiguity.
Meaning, we are arguing, but we don't realize we are arguing about two completely different things.
Exactly.
Think back to your Arrow Brew 3000 email thread.
When the marketing director says it needs to look imposing, what does it refer to?
Right.
The whole machine.
The digital display.
The packaging.
The referent is totally lost.
In GitHub, because the communication is anchored to the shared object, the disagreement is violently localized.
You are forced to point directly at the structure that is failing.
The constraint does not stifle creativity.
It acts as a focusing lens that forces human intent into an executable format.
If you are listening to this right now and you manage a team, or if you regularly find yourself walking out of collaborative meetings feeling like absolutely nothing was decided, this is the root cause.
It happens all the time.
Getting everyone on the same page is literally impossible if there is no physical or digital page to point to.
You cannot rely on a hydraulic pipe to do the job of a shared sandbox.
And if we accept that effective communication requires transforming a shared sandbox, we have to look much closer at the tools we use to dig in that sand.
We need to examine the actual anatomy of a change.
How, on a mechanical level, do we intervene in the world?
Which leads us to the atomic unit of GitHub.
The commit.
The foundational block.
Right.
For those unfamiliar, when a developer makes a change to the code and wants to save it, they package it into a commit.
But Fliction argues that almost everyone, even seasoned developers, conceptually misunderstands what a commit actually is.
We talk about it like it is a photograph.
Yeah, exactly.
A snapshot of the code frozen at a specific moment in time?
We treat it as a noun.
But structurally and mathematically, it is a verb.
A commit is not a state of being.
It is the transition from one state to another.
In the mathematical language of category theory, Fliction points out that a commit is a morphism.
Okay, morphism is a heavy piece of jargon.
Let's break that down.
Category theory is a branch of mathematics that deals with abstract structures and relationships between them, right?
How does that apply to changing software?
Think of a subway map.
Okay.
The stations themselves, Times Square, Grand Central, are the objects or the states.
But the actual train ride that takes you from Times Square to Grand Central, the path of movement, that is the morphism.
Oh, I see.
When we look at a software project, we tend to focus on the stations.
We look at version 1.0 and then we look at version 2.0.
But the version control system doesn't care about the stations.
It cares entirely about the morphisms, the thousands of tiny directional train rides that took the code base from state A to state B.
The action of changing.
That makes perfect sense.
And because developers are essentially engineering these train rides, they have a golden rule.
One logical change per commit.
They strive for what Flixing calls semantic minimality.
Semantic minimality.
Yes.
It is the pursuit of the primitive.
If you were a developer and you need to fix a broken login screen, but while you were in the code, you also notice a typo in the footer, you do not bundle those two changes together.
Because that muddies the water.
Right.
You make one distinct isolated commit for the login fix.
Then you make a separate isolated commit for the typo.
You isolate the variables.
You want the smallest possible unit of meaning so that if the login fix accidentally breaks the entire website, you can roll back that specific train ride without also deleting the typo fix.
It sounds incredibly clean and logical, but here is where Flixing pulls the rug out from under this whole system.
They point out a massive, gaping flaw in how we currently execute these changes.
There is an enormous chasm between syntax and semantics.
This is perhaps the most profound philosophical problem that software engineers wrestle with every single day, often without realizing it.
We need to separate the space of representation from the space of meaning.
Meaning syntax versus semantics.
Yes.
Syntax is the representation.
It is the literal text.
The raw typed characters, the spaces, the line breaks on the screen.
Semantics is the meaning.
It is the actual behavior of the code when it runs.
It is the intention behind the text.
So what does this all mean for version control?
If the syntax is just the raw text and semantics is the actual intention, does that mean our current systems, the massive global infrastructures like Git that run almost all modern software, are actually kind of blind?
Do they only see the ink on the page and have no idea what the story is about?
That is exactly the terrifying reality.
Tools like Git are completely unapologetically syntactic.
They track characters.
They track bytes.
They have absolutely zero understanding of concepts.
And because of this blindness, the mapping between the text on the screen and the meaning in the system is incredibly messy.
Let's illustrate this messy mapping.
Flick Sheenan talks about how the relationship is many to one.
Can you explain the refactoring problem?
Refactoring is a perfect example.
Imagine a developer looks at a piece of code that calculates the sales tax for an online cart.
The code works perfectly, but it is written in a very confusing, disorganized way.
Spaghetti code.
Exactly.
The developer spends an hour rewriting it.
They rename all the variables.
They move functions to different files.
They delete 50 lines of text and add 100 new ones.
Syntactically, the code base has undergone a massive earthquake.
Thousands of characters have changed.
But semantically?
Semantically, the behavior is completely identical.
The tax calculated at the end is exactly the same.
It is like taking a poem written in English and translating it into French.
Every single syntactic character is different.
The letters, the grammar, the spacing.
It's completely altered.
But the semantic meaning, the core emotion of the poem, remains exactly the same.
That's a great way to look at it.
But that is only one side of the problem, right?
The many-to-one issue.
Fliction also talks about regions of extreme sensitivity where the inverse happens.
Yes.
The one-to-many explosion.
Imagine a banking application with two million lines of code.
A developer goes into one file, finds a single mathematical equation,
and changes a greater-than symbol to a less-than symbol.
Oh, wow.
One keystroke.
They altered exactly one character.
Syntactically, it is a microscopic change.
It is a single byte of data.
But semantically, that one character change might invert the logic of the entire financial system,
accidentally draining millions of accounts.
That is terrifying.
It happens.
A microscopic textual change creates a catastrophic system-wide semantic collapse.
The geometry of the text simply does not match the geometry of the meaning.
I see the problem.
Because the Git system only understands the text,
it has no way of knowing that the massive refactoring was harmless,
and the tiny one-character change was a bomb.
It treats both of them just as differing amounts of changed text,
which means the human developer is forced to act as the bridge.
They have to do all this invisible cognitive labor.
It is a heavy burden.
The developer starts with a pure semantic intention in their mind.
I need to make the payment processing faster.
But they cannot just tell the system that.
Right.
They have to manually, painstakingly translate that high-level concept
into a scattershot of line-by-line textual edits across dozens of files.
Yeah.
They have to encode their meaning into syntax.
And then, when they submit that commit as a pull request to the team,
the reviewer has to do the exact opposite.
Which is just as hard.
Right.
The reviewer looks at a screen showing 500 lines of deleted text
and 600 lines of added text.
And they have to reverse-engineer it.
They have to look at the raw bricks
and try to hallucinate the shape of the cathedral
the developer was trying to build.
It is a highly lossy, exhausting process.
Computer scientists have recognized this flaw for years,
and they have tried to build better bridges.
Flixion mentions the evolution of abstract syntax trees,
or ASTs, and tools like semantic merge.
I have to admit, abstract syntax tree sounds like something out of a sci-fi novel.
How does an AST try to fix this blindness?
Think of it like diagramming a sentence in grade school.
Okay, I remember doing that.
When you just look at a sentence as raw text,
it is just a string of letters.
But when you diagram it, you break it into a tree structure.
Here's the subject noun, here's the verb phrase,
here's the modifying adjective.
An AST does this for code.
So it looks at the structure, not just the letters.
Right.
Instead of tracking raw lines of text,
it parses the code into a structural tree of logic blocks.
If a developer simply moves a function from the top of the file to the bottom,
a raw text tracker sees that as
deleted 20 lines here, added 20 lines there.
But an AST recognizes, oh, this entire logic block just moved its location.
The block itself didn't change.
So it is smarter than just tracking text.
It understands the structural grammar of the code.
It is smarter, yes.
But as Fliction critically points out,
an AST is still just a richer representation.
It is still syntax.
Diagramming a sentence might tell you where the verb is,
but it does not tell you if the sentence is a lie.
It does not reach true semantic space.
So what would a true semantic commit actually look like?
If we ever manage to build a system that understands meaning,
what are the requirements?
Fliction outlines three strict criteria for a true semantic commit.
First, it must be primitive.
It cannot be factored down into smaller independent subchanges.
It is the atomic unit of intent.
Right, the semantic minimality we talked about.
Yes.
Second, it must be complete.
It must be expressed directly in terms of behavioral relationships and outcomes,
not just a list of textual encodings.
And third, and most importantly, it must be admissible.
Admissible, meaning it obeys the overarching rules of the shared world.
You cannot just propose a change that violates the fundamental laws of physics of the system.
Like, if we are designing the AeroBrew 3000 coffee machine,
you cannot propose a water reservoir that holds negative two gallons of water.
It is inadmissible.
Exactly.
And this requirement of admissibility is the hinge point of Fliction's entire essay.
Because if we are going to allow people to propose these deep, meaningful, semantic changes to our shared world,
there must be a mechanism to decide if those changes are allowed to become reality.
You cannot just let anyone alter the fabric of the code base without checking it first.
Which leads us to the crucible, the moment of truth.
In GitHub, when you want your proposed changes to become part of the official world,
you submit what is called a pull request.
And an administrator has to click merge.
The big green button.
Yeah.
But Fliction redefines this entirely.
They don't look at the merge as just combining text.
They call it constraint closure.
Constraint closure.
Yeah.
It sounds highly academic, but it is actually a very tangible gluing operation.
Let's look at the mechanics of it.
When you propose a change, your local version of the world might work perfectly on your own computer.
But the system have a global set of constraints.
What kind of constraints?
These constraints come in two forms.
First, there are automated tests.
Scripts that run automatically to make sure your new code does not break the login system
or crash the database or violate security protocols.
The machine constraints.
Yes.
And second, there are social constraints.
The human code review.
Senior developers look at your proposal to ensure it aligns with the company's style guide,
its architectural vision, and its business goals.
So hitting merge is asking a question.
Right.
When you hit merge, the system is asking a mathematical question.
If I glue your local proposed reality onto our global shared reality, do we violate any of
these constraints?
Does the system maintain its closure?
If the automated tests pass and the humans approve, the answer is yes.
The change is merged.
It is woven into the fabric of the shared reality.
And this is where Flickshmer makes a statement that completely stopped me in my tracks.
Oh, about truth.
Yes.
They argue that in this system, truth is strictly operational.
Truth is not some abstract ideal floating in the ether.
Truth is quite literally whatever survives the gauntlet of iteration.
It is a radical, almost ruthless pragmatism.
The repository does not have a philosophical soul.
It does not have access to some divine platonic standard of perfect software.
It only has its current state, the incoming proposals, and the constraints it enforces.
Whatever proposal survives that constraint closure process, whatever passes the tests and gets
merged, that is the truth of the system.
Wait, I have to stop you there.
Because Flickshmer takes this operational definition of truth and escalates it dramatically.
They call GitHub a proto-epistemic institution.
They do.
So, epistemology is the philosophical study of how we know what is true.
Claiming that a software hosting platform is an epistemic institution feels like a massive
leap.
We are talking about bug fixes.
We are talking about moving a butter three pixels to the left.
It sounds like a stretch.
It really does.
Science has rigorous, double-blind peer review.
GitHub just has day from engineering looking at your code and clicking approve before he goes
to lunch.
How can you compare the two?
I understand the hesitation.
But if we connect this to the bigger picture, it is not an overstatement at all.
In fact, you could argue GitHub is structurally superior to how we currently conduct science.
Structurally superior to the scientific method.
Okay, you are going to have to back that up.
Let's look at what the scientific method attempts to do.
It tries to establish truth through a community of researchers proposing hypotheses, testing
those hypotheses against the constraints of physical reality, and publishing the results
for a peer review.
It is an epistemic machine.
Okay, I follow that.
But human academia has a massive, well-documented structural flaw.
It is called the file drawer problem.
Right.
Academic journals only want to publish successful experiments.
If a team of scientists spends two years testing a new cancer drug and the drug completely
fails, prestigious journals rarely want to publish a paper that says, we tried this and
nothing happened.
So the researchers just put the negative data in a file drawer and move on.
Precisely.
We throw away our negative results.
And because we throw them away, 10 years later, another team of scientists might waste two
years trying the exact same failed experiment.
Because there's no public record of the failure.
Right.
Because there is no public record that the neighborhood has already been explored and found empty.
Science loses its epistemic history.
But GitHub, entirely by accident of its design, achieves structurally what human science fails to
do.
GitHub publishes negative results by default.
Oh, I see where this is going.
When a developer submits a pull request and it fails the automated test, or Dave from engineering
rejects it because the logic is flawed, what happens to it?
It is not deleted.
It is archived.
It remains a permanent part of the repository's history.
A rejected pull request is a meticulously documented, highly searchable exploration of a semantic
neighborhood that failed the system's constraints.
The repository does not just contain the truth of the current working code.
It contains the entire graveyard of rejected hypotheses that led to that truth.
That is incredible.
It flips the concept of failure on its head.
A rejected idea isn't trash.
It is structural staff holding for the future.
It acts as a warning sign for the next developer who comes along.
It says, hey, we already tried mapping the terrain over here and we found out it breaks the database.
Don't go this way.
In the realm of statistics and probability, this is a perfect manifestation of distributed Bayesian reasoning.
Let's translate that for the listener.
Thomas Bayes was an 18th century statistician, right?
What is Bayesian updating in this context?
Bayesian reasoning is a mathematical way of updating your beliefs based on new evidence.
You start with a prior belief, in our case, the current functioning state of the code base.
Then, you encounter a hypothesis or a new evidence.
This is the incoming pull request.
The proposed change.
Right.
You evaluate that hypothesis against the constraints, assessing the probability that it is valid.
Finally, you update your belief to form a posterior.
This is the newly merged code base.
By keeping the history of both the accepted and rejected hypotheses,
GitHub acts as a collective Bayesian machine.
It doesn't just guess at the truth.
It continuously, mathematically tightens its grip on reality by evaluating evidence.
If you are listening to this and you work in a collaborative team, ask yourself a hard question.
Do you record your rejected ideas?
When your team sits in a conference room, brainstorms for an hour,
and throws out five terrible concepts to find one good one,
do you document exactly why those five concepts were terrible?
Most teams don't.
They really don't.
But if you don't, you are actively destroying valuable epistemic history.
Your team is forgetting the shake of its own constraints.
You're dooming yourselves to repeat the same bad ideas six months from now
because you didn't leave a warning sign in the file drawer.
Explicitness is what gives the transformational system its power.
The proposals are explicit, the evaluations are explicit, the tests are explicit, and the rejections are explicit.
The board is always on the table.
But what happens when we take this entire framework, this beautiful theory of morphisms and constraints and shared reality,
and we completely remove all of that explicit structure?
Here's where it gets really interesting.
Because Flixheen pivots from the rigid world of GitHub to something almost all of us interact with every single day.
On the surface, interacting with an LLM seems like the exact antithesis of GitHub.
Totally.
GitHub is syntactic, rigid, and demands perfect formatting.
Talking to an LLM is fluid, conversational, and messy.
You just type whatever you want into a chat box.
There are no branches, no explicit pull requests, no automated test suites you have to pass, and certainly no merge button.
You just chat.
But Flixheen argues that this is an illusion.
Structurally, mathematically, interacting with an LLM is identical to GitHub.
It is semantic version control.
The difference is that in an LLM, the entire process is completely implicit.
Let's break this down, because this framework permanently changed how I view prompting AI.
In the hydraulic model, we think we are sending a message to a digital person.
Hello, chat GPT.
Please write me a poem.
But Flixheen says a prompt is not a message.
A prompt is a minimal semantic perturbation of the model's implicit latent state.
We need to unpack the concept of the latent space, or this semantic manifold.
An LLM does not have a structured code base made of files and folders.
It does not have a database of facts.
Instead, it has a high-dimensional manifold.
High-dimensional manifold.
Let's ELIF-5 this.
Let's explain it like I'm 5.
Imagine a massive, unimaginably large library floating in zero gravity.
Zero gravity.
Okay.
In this library, the books are not organized alphabetically.
Instead, books that share similar meanings, or concepts, are physically pulled closer together
by a gravitational force.
The concept of coffee and the concept of morning orbit vary close to each other.
The concept of quantum mechanics is galaxies away.
So distance equals meaning.
Yes.
This gravity field operates in thousands of different dimensions simultaneously, mapping the relationships
between every word and idea the AI has ever learned.
So when I take a prompt into the chat box, I'm not searching for a specific book on a shelf.
No.
When you prompt the AI, you are tossing a heavy gravitational weight into that floating library.
Yeah.
You are applying a structural deformation to the space.
The gravity shifts, the books rearrange themselves, and the AI generates text based on whatever
concepts have been pulled to the center of your new gravitational field.
That is a stunning visual.
The conversation is a trajectory through space.
It is not a chat.
It is a flight path through a universe of concepts.
And every single time I hit enter on a new prompt, I am yanking the steering column, pushing
the AI along a specific trajectory.
And viewing it as a trajectory perfectly explains why interacting with AI can be so infuriating
and why it fails in very specific ways.
Flixin maps the common failures of LLMs directly back to the version control framework we just
discussed.
Let's look at those failures.
The most famous one is the hallucination.
When an LLM confidently invents a fake legal case or cites a scientific paper that does
not exist, why does that happen in this model?
Well, in GitHub, if you propose a change that breaks the rules, the explicit constraints, the
automated tests, block it.
The pull request is rejected.
But an LLM does not have explicit constraints.
Its constraints are implicit.
They're just baked into the model.
Right.
They are buried invisibly within its training data at whatever vague system instructions
it was given.
When a hallucination occurs, the AI has generated a reality that is locally fluent.
The grammar is perfect.
The formatting looks like a real legal document.
But it has fundamentally violated the implicit global constraint of factual accuracy.
It failed the pest, but there was no test suite to catch it.
Exactly.
It is a constraint failure.
But because there is no explicit test suite to catch it, the failure is silently merged
into the output.
It's like merging code that compiles perfectly but deletes the database.
What about Drift?
We have all experienced this.
You are using an AI to help write a novel.
For the first 20 minutes, it perfectly captures the gritty, noir detective persona you asked
for.
But an hour later, it starts responding with cheerful, generic corporate speak.
It loses the plot.
Flexion calls this trajectory instability.
Remember, your prompts are steering a flight path.
But because there is no explicit anchor, no physical chessboard to point back to your flight
path is highly susceptible to drift.
Because every prompt changes the gravity.
Right.
Every new prompt slightly alters the gravity of the latent space.
Eventually, the cumulative deformations pull you away from your original target attractor,
and the AI simply forgets the persona.
And then there's the agony of prompt sensitivity.
You ask the AI to summarize a document, and it outputs complete garbage.
You rewrite your prompt, changing exactly one word.
You change summarize to synthesize, and suddenly, it works flawlessly.
Why is it so fragile?
This is the exact same problem as the syntax to semantics gap we discussed with GitHub.
The map between the raw text you type the syntax and the gravitational shifts in the AI's
brain, the semantics, is wildly distorting.
The many-to-one or one-to-many problem.
Yes.
Just like changing one character in a million lines of code can crash a bank,
changing one word in a prompt can drastically alter the topological deformation of the latent space.
It proves that current LLMs are severely under-constrained.
They have state, they have transformations, and they have constraints, but they are all invisible.
You cannot see the repository.
You cannot see the test suite.
Which forces the user, you, sitting at your laptop, to take on an immense cognitive burden.
Because the system lacks explicit version control, you have to manually act as both the developer
and the Git system simultaneously.
I feel this in my bones.
When I use an AI for a complex task, I am constantly doing what Fliction calls manual semantic decomposition.
Breaking it down.
Yeah.
If I want the AI to write a comprehensive marketing report for our AeroBrew 3000 coffee machine,
I know I cannot just ask for the whole thing in one prompt.
It will hallucinate or drift.
I have to break my request into tiny, primitive steps.
First, write an outline for the introduction.
I read it.
I evaluate it against my internal constraints.
Okay, this is good.
That expands section one, but focus only on the target demographic.
I read it.
I evaluate it.
You are manually enforcing semantic minimality.
Yes.
I am acting as the human test suite for every single invisible commit.
It is exhausting because the AI has no internal scaffolding to do it itself.
A bad prompt is simply a bad commit.
It is either semantically overdetermined.
You ask for too many independent changes at once, causing the AI's latent space to scramble.
Or it is underdetermined.
Your intent was too vague, allowing the AI to wander into a random semantic neighborhood you didn't want.
This invisible management of state is draining, but it brings up a crucial question about how these systems prioritize information.
If you are constantly managing this invisible state with an AI, or even managing an explicit shared state on GitHub with a team of 50 developers, how does the system know what to focus on?
That's the addressing problem.
Right.
In the hydraulic email model, addressing is easy.
If I want to talk to you, I type your email address.
It is symbolic routing based on identity.
Where does a transformation go?
In transformational systems like GitHub and LLMs, addressing is not delegated to identity.
It is delegated to structure and, crucially, to recency.
Recency as address.
This concept completely reframed how I look at my software tools.
Think about a GitHub dashboard or a Jira board or any active project management tool.
The system does not push notifications to you purely based on who you are.
No, it prioritizes what was just touched.
Right.
The feed is populated by a recently updated pull request, recently modified files.
The system uses time as a sorting mechanism.
Recency acts as a probabilistic proxy for relevance.
The system fundamentally assumes that whatever is happening right now is the most important thing to the survival of the project.
If you want to communicate with a colleague on GitHub, you don't send them a private message.
You attach a transformation to the specific piece of code they're actively working on today.
You literally bump the object they are currently holding in the sandbox to get their attention.
And this is exactly how an LLM's context window works.
The AI's attention mechanism heavily weights the tokens you just typed in your most recent prompt,
and pays progressively less mathematical attention to the instructions you gave it 20 minutes ago.
Recency is the only way it knows what matters.
But substituting recency for relevance creates a massive structural vulnerability.
Structural forgetting.
If recency is the only proxy for importance, older constraints inevitably fade away.
Let's bring this back to the AeroBrew 3000 coffee machine.
Oh, back to the coffee machine.
We're building this thing.
So imagine the team agreed in week one that the machine must use a standard 120-volt power cord.
That was a firm constraint.
But for the next three months, the entire team focuses exclusively on the design of the water pump and the mobile app.
The power cord issue isn't touched.
Or it falls down the feed.
Exactly.
Because it hasn't been touched, it falls out of the recency-weighted attention field of the project board.
It structurally fades.
Six months later, the manufacturing team builds the machine with a 240-volt cord ruining the launch.
The constraint wasn't deleted.
It just lost its semantic weight.
It explains the very human feeling of being ghosted on a collaborative project.
If you were listening to this and you feel like your team consistently ignores your proposals or forgets your contributions,
it might not be office politics.
It might not be personal animosity.
You may have simply fallen out of the recency address space.
Because you aren't active enough.
Right.
If you are not actively touching the shared object, you cease to exist in the system's attention field.
So, to regain visibility, you can't just send an email complaining.
You have to go into the sandbox and touch the object again.
Which brings us to a highly measurable metric that Fliction proposes to evaluate the health of a collaborative system.
The Notification Index.
The Notification Index measures the latency of collaboration.
It is the time delta between when you propose a semantic change
and when that change is either definitively integrated into the shared world or definitively rejected.
How long does your proposal sit in limbo?
If I submit a design change for the coffee machine and it takes my manager three days to approve it,
or if it takes me ten increasingly frustrating prompts to get ChatGPT to write a working Python script,
does a high Notification Index mean my proposal is just inherently bad?
Not necessarily.
Fliction cautions that the Notification Index is a composite observable.
It mixes semantic quality with operational overhead.
It is generally composed of three distinct latencies.
Break those down for me.
The first is Attention Latency.
This asks,
Did your proposal even enter the active consideration of the evaluator?
This is the,
It got buried in my inbox latency.
Or,
in the recency model,
it fell off the front page of the dashboard before anyone looked at it.
Exactly.
The second is Processing Latency.
This is the raw operational overhead required to simply render your proposal interpretable.
If your pull request modifies 5,000 lines of code across 50 files,
or if you paste a 300-page PDF into an LLM and ask it to analyze it,
the system, whether human or machine,
simply needs time to digest the sheer volume of syntax
before it can even begin to evaluate the semantics.
The entropy is too high.
You are asking the system to swallow too big of a chunk at once.
Yes.
And the third component is Semantic Integration Latency.
This is the core epistemic work.
Once the system understands what you're proposing,
how long does it take to determine if it fits the constraints?
Ah, so this is the actual evaluation part.
Right.
If your proposal is minimal,
elegantly coded,
and perfectly aligned with the project's goals,
this latency is near zero.
The human reviewer glances at it,
sees it as safe,
and hits merge.
But,
if your proposal is messy,
entangled with other features,
and fundamentally conflicts with existing truths in the system,
this latency skyrockets.
It requires extensive human negotiation,
meetings,
and rewriting to untangle the conflict.
So,
if your team has a high notification index,
if everything feels like it moves through molasses,
you have to diagnose which latency is the culprit.
Are people just ignoring the dashboard?
Are the proposals too massive to read?
Or are the proposals constantly violating the rules?
You have to isolate the bottleneck.
And solving this requires us to look beyond the software itself.
We have to look at the invisible human elements that govern how teams actually function.
Fliction outlines this in what they call the extended stack.
The extended stack is where Fliction's theory bridges the gap between software engineering and human sociology.
There are three layers in this stack that dictate whether a proposed change successfully survives the merge.
The first layer is theoretical synthesis.
Theoretical synthesis.
This happens when two people propose changes that clash, right?
Yes.
What developers call a merge conflict.
Imagine two engineers on the AeroBrew team.
Engineer A submits a change that makes the water heater draw more power to heat up faster.
Engineer B submits a change that reduces the overall power supply to save manufacturing costs.
Both changes pass their local tests.
But globally they conflict.
Exactly.
You cannot have a hydrod heater on a low power supply.
The system breaks.
So, how does the team resolve it?
Do they just argue until one person gives up?
A low-functioning team will do exactly that.
They will view it as a zero-sum game and pick a winner.
But theoretical synthesis is the ability of the team to lift those conflicting realities into a higher-order structure where they can both coexist.
How does that look in practice?
Instead of fighting over the power supply, the team might synthesize a new architecture.
A smart heater that only draws high power when the rest of the machine is idle.
Theoretical synthesis is the intellectual capacity to evolve the system's architecture rather than just fighting over the current layout.
I love that framing.
It is not about compromise.
It is about synthesis.
You don't chop the house in half.
You build a bigger roof that covers both ideas.
The second layer of the extended stack is the entropy budget.
Every proposed transformation carries a certain amount of semantic entropy.
Entropy in this context means ambiguity, degrees of freedom, unresolved questions, and potential side effects.
A system, whether it is a code base, a human team, or an LLM, can only absorb a finite amount of entropy before it destabilizes.
It has a strict cognitive load limit.
But this perfectly explains why massive, vague corporate proposals get deferred forever.
If I walk into a meeting and hand my executive team a 70-page document proposing a complete top-to-bottom pivot of our company's marketing strategy,
that proposal carries a massive entropy load.
It's too much to process.
There are thousands of unresolved variables.
The team's collective entropy budget cannot absorb it.
They will say, let's form a committee to review this, which is corporate speak for, this will never happen.
But if I propose one minimal primitive change, let's allocate $500 to test this one specific ad platform for one week,
the entropy is incredibly low.
It is safe.
It can be cleanly incorporated.
It proves that the developer's golden rule of semantic minimality, making small atomic commits,
is not just an aesthetic preference for neat freaks.
It is a vital, mathematically sound strategy for operating within the strict entropy constraints of any collaborative medium.
Which flows seamlessly into the final and perhaps most fascinating layer of the extended stack.
Rapport.
We usually think of rapport as a soft skill.
It means you get along with your co-workers, you chat about the weekend, you have a good vibe.
But Flitchner redefines rapport as a structural engineering concept.
They call it a shared compression scheme.
Viewing rapport as a compression scheme is a brilliant application of information theory.
Let's look at how it functions.
When a team has high rapport, they share a vast repository of priors, expectations, historical context, and unwritten conventions.
Because they possess this dense shared context, a complex transformation can be proposed with very little explicit detail.
The teammates just get it.
They can instantly decode the intent behind a sparse proposal.
It acts as an entropy reducer.
Let's say you and I have been co-hosting this podcast for five years.
We have incredibly high rapport.
If I send you a script and just leave a comment that says, punch this up, it feels too academic, you know exactly what I mean.
I know exactly what you want.
Right.
You know my sense of humor.
You know our audience's tolerance for jargon.
You know exactly what punch-up entails in our specific shared world.
I do not have to write a 10-page manual explaining how to be funny.
The communication is highly compressed.
Exactly.
The shared compression scheme did the heavy lifting.
But if we have low rapport, if we just met today, and I tell you to punch it up, you have no shared context.
You might add knock-knock jokes.
You might add aggressive sarcasm.
I might ruin the whole episode.
You might.
To prevent that, I would have to over-explain everything.
I would have to explicitly define the boundaries of the humor.
This lack of compression increases the cognitive load, spikes the entropy of the request, and drastically slows down the notification index.
So building rapport on a team isn't just an HR initiative to make people happy.
Rapport is a literal structural multiplier on your team's operational bandwidth.
It allows you to move faster because you don't have to explicitly map every single coordinate of every single brick.
And Flixion shows how this compositionality, this ability to manage entropy and reuse structure, doesn't just apply to teams of people.
It happens at the absolute micro level of the individual user interacting with their own computer.
This brings us to the micromechanics of the interface.
We spend our days interacting with operating systems, but we rarely examine the philosophical implications of our keystrokes.
Flixion points out that something as mundane as the clipboard, the Criterial-C and Stritural-V mechanism, is actually a profound piece of semantic machinery.
This realization completely shifted how I view my daily workflow.
I have used a computer for 30 years, and I have never once thought of the clipboard as anything more than a dumb temporary storage box,
a place to hold text while I move it from a PDF to an email.
But Flixion argues that, especially when you look at advanced clipboard managers that save a history of everything you copy,
the clipboard is actually a primitive form of semantic macro composition.
Think about the action.
When you highlight a block of text and copy it, you are not just duplicating ink.
You are extracting a fragment of structure from a specific context.
You are isolating a reusable deformation.
Copying is an act of abstraction.
You are lifting a concept out of its local reality.
And pasting is an act of reapplication.
You are taking that abstracted structure and forcing it into a new reality.
We are constantly building our own personal, weakly regulated repositories of semantic macros.
Let's say I write a really effective email, declining a meeting invite.
It is polite.
It is firm.
It gets the job done.
I copy it.
The next time someone invites me to a meeting I don't want to attend, I paste it, change the name, and hit send.
You're running a script.
I am.
I am not writing an email.
I am deploying a stored operation.
I am taking a semantic transformation that I know works,
a transformation that survived the social constraints of previous interactions,
and applying it to a new problem.
The exact same logic applies to a developer using a command line interface, like Bash.
When a developer hits the up arrow on their keyboard to bring up the last command they typed,
they are not just looking at a text log.
They are retrieving an executable transformation from their personal history,
slightly adjusting its parameters, and applying it again.
They are navigating a structured, historical ledger of operations.
It is a personal version control system, but it is a weak one,
because there are no constraints enforcing whether my copy-paste is actually a good idea.
The clipboard doesn't run an automated test to see if pasting that angry email into a chat with my boss is a career-ending move.
No, it just lets you do it.
Right.
Which leads directly to the ultimate vision of Fliction's paper.
This raises an important question.
If this transformational model is so powerful from the macro level of teams down to the micro level of the clipboard,
what should the future of our digital tools look like?
Fliction's envisions a paradigm shift where the boundaries between these different modes of interaction completely dissolve.
A unified interface.
Right now, writing a document in Word, writing a script in Python, and managing a project in GitHub
feel like three completely different universes with different rules.
But Fliction is saying they are all fundamentally the exact same mechanism.
Whether you are copy-pasting a sentence, prompting an LLM to generate code,
or a global society determining the validity of a scientific claim,
the underlying architecture is identical.
You are proposing a transformation, checking it against a set of constraints,
and integrating it into a shared world.
The future of tooling will move away from the idea of creating content from scratch on a blank page.
It will move toward the structured reuse, parameterization, and recombination of validated operations.
You won't just type text.
You will weave together threads of logic that have already survived the crucible of constraint closure.
We have gone on an absolutely massive journey today.
Let's try to synthesize the entire architecture of what we've covered.
We started by dismantling the hydraulic illusion of communication,
the pervasive Shannon-era idea that we are just throwing encoded messages down a copper pipe,
hoping the person on the other end decodes our intent.
We saw how that hydraulic model forces human beings to internalize state,
leading to the chaotic archaeology of the 40-reply email thread.
And we contrasted that with transformational communication,
exemplified by GitHub, which externalizes the state.
It puts the chessboard on the table,
forcing us to communicate through constrained primitive morphisms actions that change the board.
We took a hard look at the terrifying gap between syntax,
the dumb raw texter systems track, and semantics,
the actual meaning and intent behind our actions.
We explored the concept of admissibility,
redefining truth not as a philosophical absolute, but as an operational reality.
Truth is whatever survives the constraint closure of the merge.
We then took that rigid, explicit framework
and applied it to the fluid, messy world of interacting with large language models.
We revealed how prompts are not conversational messages,
but semantic perturbations in a high-dimensional latent space,
and how the lack of explicit constraints leads to hallucinations and drift.
We unpacked the vulnerability of relying on the recency as a blind proxy for relevance,
and how that leads to structural forgetting.
And finally, we explored the extended stack synthesis, entropy, and rapport,
proving that human sociology and emotional intelligence
are actually structural engineering requirements for a functioning system.
Before we close, it is worth briefly mentioning a final note Flexion makes at the end of the essay
regarding a research initiative called the Tartan Program.
Oh, I almost forgot about that.
Yeah, Flexion points out that while GitHub is an incredible tool,
it is essentially a primitive, accidental version of a much more rigorous architecture being formalized by Tartan.
This program focuses on the mathematical, iterative tightening of admissibility conditions
for truth-seeking across decentralized networks.
It is a vital signal that this essay isn't just abstract philosophy or navel-gazing.
These concepts are actively serving as the blueprints for the next generation
of how both artificial and human systems will establish shared realities.
It is a staggering shift in perspective.
If you take one practical thing away from this deep dive, let it be this.
The next time you sit down to collaborate on a complex project with your team,
or the next time you open up an AI interface to try and solve a hard problem,
actively stop yourself from thinking of it as a chat.
Stop trying to send a message.
Look for the shared object.
Ask yourself, what is the specific, minimal, primitive transformation I am proposing to our shared reality right now?
Demand explicitness from your tools and your teams.
Do not rely on everyone holding the same complex, fragile state in their individual minds.
Put the board on the table.
Make the constraints visible.
Exactly.
If the x-ray machine is broken and the muddy waters are rising,
you have to build a better way to agree on the reality in front of you.
Which brings me to a final, slightly provocative thought I want to leave you to mull over.
We have spent this entire time talking about software, AI, and project management.
But what about our personal lives?
Oh, applying this to relationships.
Yes.
If transformational communication requires explicit constraints to function smoothly,
like GitHub's automated test suites catching bugs before they merge into the main project,
what are the unspoken, implicit constraints you are enforcing in your everyday human relationships?
When your partner or your friend proposes a change to your shared dynamic,
are you evaluating it against invisible rules they don't even know exist?
And what would happen to the entropy of your relationships if you actually made those constraints explicit?
It is a terrifying but necessary question to ask if we want to build shared worlds that actually last.
That's richly said.
We've gone from the muddy waters of a 40 email thread to the absolute clarity of a shared, transformed world.
Thank you so much for joining us on this deep dive.
Keep building your world, one minimal, admissible change at a time.